בוקר טוב. Boker tov. All right, so we are today we're doing
דף ל"ז Daf Lamed Zayin and not in נדרים Nedarim but in
נזיר, Nazir, and we are in the middle of discussing of this
major סוגיא sugya which is often an early סוגיא sugya learned in
when learning כשרות Kashrus because the first sort of concepts we did
yesterday, we had did two, and today we're turning to the third,
which is really the key. The first two that we did yesterday
were
היתר מצטרף לאיסור, Heter Mitztaref L'Issur, which is under some areas of
הלכה, halacha,
specifically נזיר Nazir seems to be the one according to רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, where we actually say that if you have איסור Issur
and היתר Heter side by side or maybe somehow mixed together but
without concerns about whether taste is spreading or anything like that, that
even if the amount of the היתר Heter comes to the non-forbidden
food comes together to give you the full amount of minimum size
for a transgression to get מלקות malkos and so on. So the
example is at specifically by נזיר, Nazir, it says משרת ענבים, Mishrat
Anavim, something that is literally soaked in grapes, but we're interpreting, we're
giving an example of food soaked in wine, bread soaked in wine,
that because you have the bread and the wine together, even if
you have a כזית k'zayis not of the wine but of the
combination, you get lashes. Now is that a principle of היתר מצטרף
לאיסור? Heter Mitztaref L'Issur? That you're really חייב chayav on the grapes
or on the wine but this the bread adds to the minimum
amount? Or is it that something else is forbidden, not just wine
is forbidden but a mixture of wine is forbidden which is implied
by the word משרת? Mishrat? So that's you could go either way.
But that's one principle of היתר מצטרף לאיסור Heter Mitztaref L'Issur which
the גמרא Gemara said applies only by נזיר Nazir according to presumably
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, we'll clarify that briefly, and maybe
by offering off חמץ chametz on the altar where it says כי
כל שאור וכל דבש, Ki Kol Se'or V'chol Devash, so even a
little bit of bread and a little of מצה matzah combined makes
the minimum size, or חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach according to רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, כל מחמצת Kol Machmetzet
which also might not really be the principle of היתר מצטרף לאיסור,
Heter Mitztaref L'Issur, might more be the principle that not only is
חמץ chametz forbidden but mixtures with חמץ chametz are forbidden and for
example there you might not get כרת kares or you don't get
כרת kares in the case of תערובת חמץ. ta'aroves chametz. So that's
one principle of היתר מצטרף לאיסור. Heter Mitztaref L'Issur. That we're going
to put aside. The more interesting principle that the גמרא Gemara spent
most of the time yesterday discussing was כזית בכדי אכילת פרס, K'zayis
B'chdei Achilas Pras, which was a case where it started with cases
where things were mixed together and the problematic, the forbidden food was
ניכר, nikar, was presumably visible and distinct. So for example this כותח
הבבלי, kutach habavli, this dip on פסח Pesach which is you know
some type of a sour milk plus bread crumbs, and there the
idea was was that even if that you transgress by eating the
forbidden food that is that is mixed within the permissible food. The
permissible food doesn't make it like you transgress for every כזית k'zayis
that you eat, every כזית k'zayis of the dip that you eat,
but if you eat enough dip that you've eaten a כזית k'zayis
of חמץ, chametz, you would transgress assuming that you would eat it
in a normal way and fast enough in order that you ate
it within the time it takes to eat half a loaf of
bread, which is eight or nine ביצים, beitzim, which is who knows
what it is, ten minutes let's say.
So that is a different principle, and that principle is one where
it does not turn the היתר heter into איסור, issur, it just
says that even in a case of a mixture you still pay
attention to the forbidden food that is there and you would actually
transgress were you to eat it fast enough. Now if it's now
started with cases of it being ניכר nikar so it wasn't saying
something about ביטול, bittul, but the case we ended with yesterday was
a case of grain being mixed with grain where it was not
distinct, it was not ניכר, nikar, and you would normally have applied
a principle of ביטול bittul and nevertheless the גמרא Gemara felt that
the the idea of כזית בכדי אכילת פרס K'zayis B'chdei Achilas Pras
is relevant. So one of the things that the גמרא Gemara seems
to be saying is that this principle not only tells you that
you know that if you eat it slowly in a mixture of
other things it's considered enough that you combine the little pieces, but
it's also telling you you know for the purposes of lashes, but
it's also telling you the idea that it that something does not
become בטל batel when it is in the mixture, which wasn't clear
from earlier in the discussion. That because it's about mixtures and proportions
and mixtures it's telling you that ביטול bittul does not occur when
it is that degree of you know of a proportion of the
mixture. Okay so that now הלכה halacha we probably don't say that
or we don't say that when it is מין במינו, min b'mino,
same type and type even though that was the last case the
גמרא Gemara applied it to. Okay we probably there needs to be
something that actually other that in addition contributes to it not becoming
בטל batel specifically that it has to give off taste in the
mixture. So if it's all the same type being mixed, although that
was the last case in the גמרא, Gemara, I'm just telling you
as a matter of הלכה halacha we do not say that כזית
בכדי אכילת פרס K'zayis B'chdei Achilas Pras that proportion is enough to
prevent ביטול. bittul. We say the actual prevention of ביטול bittul requires
that it be מין באינו מינו, min b'eino mino, like and unlike
being mixed together and that that... The problematic food gives off taste,
gives off taste,
and it's the taste that it's giving off that prevents ביטול. bittul.
Okay, but that is an idea that even when it occurs in
mixtures, maybe if it's not ניכר, nikar, but that with that proportion
you would actually transgress and transgress enough to get lashes even though
you're not eating the thing directly, you're only eating it in a
mixture. Okay, and now the גמרא's Gemara going to continue to the
third category, and that is going to be, that remains very relevant
להלכה le-halacha and I'll clarify even more why in a few minutes.
Okay, but the third category we now turn to is the one
that is the most fundamental for laws of כשרות, kashrut, and that's
a principle called טעם כעיקר, taam ke-ikar, the taste is like the
thing itself. Okay,
often abbreviated as... like this.
Okay,
that's like one probably the biggest, the most common abbreviation you're going
to get in כשרות, kashrut, טעם כעיקר. taam ke-ikar. Okay, also you
have to understand that it's כעיקר. ke-ikar. Some people think they're talking
about the taste of a cookie or something.
So anyway, but
or a loaf of bread, I should say, a ככר. kikar. Anyway,
so anyway, so that the idea is that the taste of something
counts like the thing itself. Now there are two scenarios of טעם
כעיקר. taam ke-ikar. One is something that is pure taste. I mean
everything that is taste is some essence of the thing itself. But
from our human experience, we experience not on a scientific level, we
experience things in two different realities. We experience something that we relate
to as just taste. For example, I drop a piece of meat
into a pot of stew and then I take out the piece
of meat. And it looks roughly the same size and even if
it looks a little smaller, I don't consider, I don't experience that
as though some meat is dissolved in the stew. I experience it
as that some of the taste of the meat went into the
soup. Okay, or in a more extreme case, I cook meat in
a pot and then I cook vegetables in the pot, we say
the taste went into the pot and from the pot into the
vegetables. That's for people who know כשרות, kashrut, but before you even
get to that, a good example would be I drop the meat
in the soup and then I take it out, or an example
the גמרא's Gemara going to have is I have grapes in water
and I let them sit long enough and then the water takes
on a little bit of a grape taste. That's pure טעם. taam.
Another taste, that another גמרא, Gemara, not this גמרא's Gemara not going
to distinguish between the two categories I'm talking about, but another גמרא
Gemara does and I just wanted to lay out that we're talking
about both. So that's called טעמו ולא ממשו. taamo ve-lo mamasho. The
other category is where it's the taste, but it's the taste because
the thing itself is dissolved, you just can't identify the thing. So
you go ahead and you would let's say, well one would be
you dip your, you dip your bread into wine and then you're
tasting the wine, it doesn't feel like you're drinking wine, it doesn't
feel like there's wine that's directly there, it's absorbed but it's sort
of the taste. There you can even actually see though it's, you
know, it's marked. But another example would be I don't know, you
pour milk into your, we're going to get a case like this,
into your chicken soup. Okay? So it completely dissolves, okay, but you
have the taste of milk in it, that would be a בשר
בחלב basar be-chalav situation, but that would be טעמו וממשו. taamo u-mamasho.
You wouldn't just say I have the taste of milk, you'd say
I have the milk here. But you would still need the חידוש
chiddush of טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikar because you might say in that
case also maybe the milk becomes בטל. batel. And this points to
two ideas behind the חידוש chiddush of טעם כעיקר. taam ke-ikar. One
idea is that in the case where you took the meat in
and took it out, you might say that if all it gives
off is taste, that halachically is nothing. That's not meat, that's taste
of meat, and that halachically has no status. For example, there's a
discussion in the גמרא Gemara about what about ריח? reiach? Let's say
I go and I you know, have my loaf of bread near
some frying bacon, and the loaf of bread, it's not in it,
it's just nearby, absorbs some of the smell you know into the
bread because it's right near and it gets some of that smell.
Is that forbidden? Is that like I'm eating little pieces of bacon?
So the same could be the meat falls into the pot and
I take it out. Maybe we just halachically define that as taste
of meat and not as meat, and it's nothing. So the first
חידוש chiddush of טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikar is even in that case
of טעמו ולא ממשו, taamo ve-lo mamasho, when it gives off its
taste, it's considered like no, little pieces of meat are now mixed
in the stew even though you can't see them and you never
saw them, you just saw piece come in and a piece go
out. Nevertheless, there's little pieces of that meat in the stew and
if it was חזיר chazir there's little pieces of חזיר chazir in
the stew. That's one חידוש. chiddush. By טעמו וממשו taamo u-mamasho there's
a second level of חידוש. chiddush. By טעמו וממשו taamo u-mamasho the
חידוש chiddush is is that you might say let's say it's let's
say it was a case not of milk and meat which is
more complicated, we'll get to it, but let's say it's a case
of I don't know I have
some you know some liquefied חזיר chazir that I pour into my
chicken soup. Okay? So there you might say well of course חזיר
chazir is in my chicken soup, why do I need a חידוש
chiddush of טעם כעיקר? taam ke-ikar? But the point is ah, but
you might say but I can't see it, it's lost its identity.
You can't see it, I can taste it, but I can, but
you might say since I can't see it and I can't identify
it and I can't point to it and it's not physically distinct,
it's completely dispersed throughout, maybe it loses its identity, maybe it's בטל.
batel. So part of what טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikar says. is there
is the fact that I can still taste with every bit of
soup that I taste, I taste חזיר chazir tells me the חזיר
chazir has not gone out of existence. The חזיר chazir is still
present. Okay, so you get it. There are two ideas. One is
that the taste is the thing itself. Don't say it's some different
thing, even if you remove the piece of חזיר chazir and you
just have the taste behind, you still have pieces of חזיר chazir
in your soup. And the other is, is that it is not
בטל batel even if you can't see it, it's still considered to
be present. Just one second. Now both of those ideas would suggest
that you only transgress for the actual quantity of חזיר chazir that's
in the soup. None of that says this is why it's distinct
from היתר מצטרף לאיסור. heter mitztaref l'issur. None of it is saying
that the soup becomes חזיר, chazir, it just says that the presence
of the taste of חזיר chazir is still חזיר. chazir. It hasn't
disappeared, even if, you know, the חזיר chazir has been taken out
of the soup, this taste is still little pieces of חזיר chazir
are still there. Fine, but you only transgress presumably for the amount
of חזיר chazir that is there. That's point number one. Point number
two, that's what you would say, that's what almost all the ראשונים
rishonim say except there's a רא"ש Rosh that we're not going to
discuss, that you only transgress for the amount of חזיר chazir that's
there. Point number two, though, is that some ראשונים rishonim say that
this is a new איסור. issur. This is not it is just
taste. And it's טעם כעיקר. ta'am k'ikar. It's like the thing itself,
but it isn't the thing itself actually. There's always the question of
כ. ke. Does כ ke mean equals to or does כ ke
mean similar to? Okay? So some ראשונים rishonim say that actually this
is a new איסור. issur. It's called an איסור טעם. issur ta'am.
The essence is בטל batel or in the case of טעם ולא
ממשו ta'am v'lo mamasho maybe there's no essence there. But it doesn't
matter. If you're tasting חזיר chazir that originated from your חזיר, chazir,
not fake bacon bits, if you're tasting חזיר chazir that originated from
your חזיר, chazir, in the same way it's אסור assur to eat
physical חזיר, chazir, it's אסור assur to eat something that has the
taste of חזיר. chazir. But it's not the איסור issur of חזיר.
chazir. It's a new איסור issur called an איסור טעם. issur ta'am.
So those are the different ideas. Number one, that taste still counts
like the thing, like little pieces of the thing. Number two is
even if you can't see it and identify it and it's not
distinct, it's still present, it's not בטל. batel. Both of those things
would be saying that it's little pieces of חזיר chazir here and
you transgress for eating little pieces of חזיר. chazir. Okay, but it
is the איסור issur of חזיר. chazir. The alternative approach is saying,
no, it is בטל, batel, it's not the thing itself, but the
same way you can't eat חזיר, chazir, there's another איסור issur that
you can't eat something that has the taste of חזיר. chazir. Okay,
two very different approaches. Charlie, you had your hand up.
Why did the mention of kosher bacon bits, how would a פרום
frum Jew have even known the taste of חזיר? chazir?
So you get a non-Jew to taste you or to taste it
for you, okay?
You trust a non-Jew.
Yeah, and that's a different סוגיא. sugya. Yeah?
I have another question. So you're saying this is only positive there's
a טעם. ta'am. But let's say your thing is so spicy that
you're not going to like taste the חזיר chazir in there?
Or let's say you've you
get a נטל"פ natlap it doesn't have a taste anyway?
Right, so those things you would not be חייב chayav in those
cases.
Even if you have like a lot of נטל"פ natlap in there?
Like, you know, how does that?
Correct. Well, no, if you have it בעין b'ayin to the point
that it's a majority and it's not בטל, batel, that's different. But
if it's בטל batel and it's dissolved?
Then you go by simple majority?
Yeah, I mean
if it's dissolved.
If it's ניכר, nikar, then that's another reason it's not בטל. batel.
So let's read this.
How's טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar different from נב"נ? naban? Completely different. נב"נ
naban is a subset of טעם כעיקר. ta'am k'ikar. What happens when
the טעם ta'am passes through a number of stages. Okay, but that's
not our issue.
I have another clarifying question. So according to this last סברא, sevara,
bacon bits which are themselves kosher would be אסור assur because of
the טעם? ta'am?
No, that's what I said. The טעם ta'am that is like the
essence is when it originated from a thing that was itself.
It has to always originate.
Yes, correct, correct. It's not anything that tastes like חזיר, chazir, it
is the taste of חזיר. chazir.
Even according to the סברא sevara that says it's a new איסור.
issur.
Exactly. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so let's start from this. אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye.
So we'll reread from like six lines from the top. Said אביי
Abaye to רב דימי, Rav Dimi, ממאי דהאי משרה לאיתויי היתר מצטרף
לאיסור, mimai d'hai mishrah l'aitu'ei heter mitztaref l'issur, how do you know
משרה mishrah is coming to tell you this principle
that the היתר heter combines with איסור issur to the minimum size
of a
כזית? kazayit? דילמא לטעם כעיקר הוא דאתא, dilma l'ta'am k'ikar hu de'ata,
maybe it's for this principle of טעם כעיקר. ta'am k'ikar. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולאביי מעיקרא כקשיא ליה מאי דקאמר רב דימי. u'l'Abaye
me'ikara k'kashya lei mai d'ka'amar Rav Dimi. At first, he was bothered
what רב דימי Rav Dimi said that he wanted a limit
of היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref l'issur only to נזיר. Nazir. ואביי
v'Abaye was arguing that it should apply more broadly. וקמותיב ליה כלהו
הני תיובתי, v'kamotiv lei kulhu hani tivusei, and he asked a whole
range of questions to apply to apply היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref
l'issur more broadly. הדר אמר ליה ליתי טעם כעיקר? hadar amar lei
leitei ta'am k'ikar? And now he wants to say oh maybe we
don't even say that there's a principle of היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter
mitztaref l'issur at all, maybe it's just a principle of טעם כעיקר?
ta'am k'ikar? Like make up your mind, what are you saying? So
גמרא Gemara says no, בתר דשני ליה, basar d'shani lei, after he
answered him and explained to him how we could limit
היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref l'issur just to נזיר Nazir that we
don't apply it more broadly, אמר ליה, amar lei, so he's asked
him from a different perspective. Maybe rather than applying היתר מצטרף לאיסור
heter mitztaref l'issur all over, we'll say the opposite, maybe we don't
have it as a principle at all. אמר ליה ליתי טעם כעיקר.
amar lei leitei ta'am k'ikar. Okay so אמר ליה ליתי amar lei
leitei wait a
minute I read the
top הדר אמר ליה ליתי טעם כעיקר hadar amar lei leitei ta'am
k'ikar בתר דשני ליה basar d'shani lei אמר ליה דילמא לטעם כעיקר
הוא דאתא. amar lei dilma l'ta'am k'ikar hu de-ata. הא דקאמר ליה,
Ha d’ka’amar leh, the whole problem is he didn’t טעם כעיקר, Ta’am
k’Ikkar, that’s what he’s... wait a minute. That’s what he’s coming to
ask. I understand it.
הדר אמר ליה Hadar amar leh so וקא מוסיף וקאני... v’ka’mosif v’ka’ani...
ממאי... mi’may... שיש... she’yesh... Oh, I skipped a line.
Okay, got it.
Okay, okay. Wait a minute.
Let me... hold on. ובעי מיניה כולהו קושיות דאמר רב דימי וקא
מוסיף וקאני
תשובה הדר אמר ליה ליתן טעם כעיקר. U’va’ei mineih kuleihu kushyos d’amar
Rav Dimi v’ka’mosif v’ka’ani teshuvah hadar amar leh leitein ta’am k’Ikkar. Right,
I’m sorry, you’re right. That’s part of the question. Question mark. So
the answer is no, בתר דשני ליה ואמר ליה דילמא ליתן טעם
כעיקר. Basro deshni leh v’amar leh dilma leitein ta’am k’Ikkar. Yeah, I
just reread the previous line. Okay, yes, after he gave him the
answers, then Abaye came back and said, okay, so then maybe everything
is just for טעם כעיקר Ta’am k’Ikkar and we don’t have a
principle of היתר מצטרף לאיסור Heter mitztaref l’issur at all, הוא דאתא.
hu de’ata. ומכדי תניא. U’michdi tanya. And now we’re going to show
where we get from מקרא mikra the idea of טעם כעיקר. Ta’am
k’Ikkar. Okay, מקרא mikra we find טעם כעיקר. Ta’am k’Ikkar. משרת ענבים
במים Mishrat anavim bamayim and here it’s more literally the פסוק pasuk
about משרת ענבים, mishrat anavim, something that is the grapes are themselves
submerged. Okay, that if somebody
submerged grapes, immersed them in water, ויש בהן טעם יין v’yeish bahen
ta’am yayin and the water’s taken on the taste of wine, חייב,
chayav, you’re חייב. chayav. ומכאן אתה דן לכל איסורין שבתורה. U’mikan atah
dan l’chol issurin sheba’Torah. And now you can apply this principle that
the same way you’re חייב chayav on the water, you’d be חייב
chayav on all prohibition, in all... so we’re going to take a
look, okay? We’re going to use this as a paradigm for all
other איסורין issurin of the תורה. Torah. ומה נזיר שאין איסורו איסור
עולם, U’mah Nazir she’ein issuro issur olam, a
נזיר Nazir is not forever, נזירות neziros ends after thirty days. ואין
איסורו איסור הנאה v’ein issuro issur hana’ah and a נזיר Nazir is
not prevented from getting benefit from wine. ויש היתר לאיסורו v’yeish heter
l’issuro
and it will become permissible. Now, how is permissible different than it’s
not for forever? So תוספות Tosafos says what it means it’ll become
permissible is that he can go to a חכם chacham and get
it הותר, hutar, okay? So there’s another explanation though that it means
יש היתר yeish heter to create the איסור, issur, that you’re allowed
to become a נזיר. Nazir. There’s no prohibition to put yourself into
that situation. We’ll see what that’s contrasted to. That’s actually a nice
explanation.
In non-kosher and you’re kosher, which you can’t do, right?
Well, let’s take a look at the next example. Okay, in that
case, it has all those leniencies and עשה בו טעם כעיקר, asah
bo ta’am k’Ikkar, the טעם ta’am is treated like the עיקר. Ikkar.
כלאי הכרם, Kil’ei hakerem, how about כלאים kilayim of the vine, שאיסורו
איסור עולם, she’issuro issur olam, they never become permissible. ואיסורו איסור הנאה
v’issuro issur hana’ah and you can’t get benefit from כלאים. kilayim. ואין
היתר לאיסורם, v’ein heter l’issuram, that reads very nicely, you’re not allowed,
it’s not permissible to create כלאים, kilayim, that’s a very nice read.
Okay. אינו דין שיעשה בו טעם כעיקר, eino din sheye’aseh bo ta’am
k’Ikkar, how much more so would we say טעם כעיקר? Ta’am k’Ikkar?
Okay, because even in more weighty prohibitions, and pretty much every prohibition
is more weighty than נזיר, Nazir, because חזיר chazir or anything like
that is an איסור עולם, issur olam, right? The only thing that
would not be an איסור עולם issur olam would be let’s say
חדש chadash or something. Okay, but anyway, so... והוא הדין לערלה בשנים
v’hu hadin l’Orlah bishnayim and ערלה Orlah is like this in two
ways. It’s an איסור לעולם issur l’olam and it’s an איסור הנאה,
issur hana’ah, but it’s not... it has היתר לאיסורה heter l’issurah according
to that read, you’re allowed to create ערלה, Orlah, you’re allowed to
plant a tree. Okay. So... anyway, so if it applies by נזיר
Nazir which is a very lenient איסור, issur, it should certainly apply
by all other things. Okay, so that reads מקרא, mikra, מקרא mikra
is not telling you bread plus wine or bread plus grapes we
add them together to get the כזית. kezayit. It’s telling you if
there’s the טעם ta’am of grapes in the bread or the טעם
ta’am of grapes in the water, it still is like wine and
it still is like grapes and you still transgress. Now, how much
do you transgress for? Every כזית kezayit of bread that you eat,
every רביעית revi’is of water that you eat, or do you only
transgress when you’ve eaten enough of the absorbed טעם? ta’am? The way
I laid it out conceptually you would say only when you’ve eaten
enough of the absorbed טעם ta’am and in that way it’s different
from
היתר מצטרף לאיסור, Heter mitztaref l’issur, yes.
I have this image in my mind, I’ve got these grapes in
the water, the water’s absorbing the טעם. ta’am. Yeah. But the color
of the water is changing and isn’t that like a ניכר, nikkar,
so it’s like this ממש... mamash...
Well again, ניכר nikkar is... there’s two types of ניכר. nikkar. ניכר
Nikkar means... no, no, no, it’s a good question. ניכר Nikkar when
we say ניכר nikkar doesn’t even get you into any discussions of
ביטול, bitul, that doesn’t just mean that you can tell that it
was mixed in. It actually means that it is distinct. It is
distinct. So you cannot say that this little piece of חזיר chazir
is בטל batel if, what do you mean it’s בטל? batel? It’s
right here, I can take it out, it has its own identity.
If something gives off טעם ta’am or gives off a color, okay,
the reason ביטול bitul becomes an issue and you need the חידוש
chiddush of טעם כעיקר, Ta’am k’Ikkar, the reason ביטול bitul becomes an
issue is because it is not distinct. You know it’s dispersed, but
it’s not distinct. So you could say okay, but it’s one big
mass, this thing does not... is not distinct, so basically I have
water, I have water that has the טעם ta’am of wine and
the color of wine, but I don’t have wine here because I
can’t take out the wine. What I have is wine-flavored water. Okay,
so that’s why ביטול bitul is a possibility and you need the
חידוש chiddush of טעם כעיקר. Ta’am k’Ikkar. Now in terms of the
question of what is something made its presence felt by טעם... ta’am...
by sight, by appearance, rather than by taste, would that function similar
to טעם ta'am to prevent ביטול? bitul? What if there's no טעם?
ta'am? Once we introduce the חידוש chiddush of טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar
and say the fact that it can be sensed, its presence prevents
ביטול, bitul, would we say the same if it changed the color?
So actually the general rule is interestingly that we say this by
things that are not food-related. So for example, if something gets mixed
up in the water of a מקוה mikvah or דם dam blood
and water get mixed up to be sprinkled on the מזבח mizbeach
altar, we define is there still the דם dam present, the blood
of the קרבן korban sacrifice by whether the water has taken on
the color of the blood. And the reason my sort of explanation
for this now that you're asking is, is that
our primary sight for those that have all their senses is our
primary sense of experiencing the world is sight, right? That's the primary
means through which we experience the world. So if you wanted to
talk about something's identity and is it still present, the first thing
you would say is can I see it? Can I see somehow
that it made an impact? That's something you can see and experience
at a distance and so on. So when it's not food-related, by
other cases, when there's a תערובת ta'aroves mixture and you want to
say is the thing בטל batel or is it clearly still there,
the actual הלכה halacha defines it by whether it's visible, whether it's
not distinct, but whether it's made its presence visible through changing the
color. Whereas by food, food is primarily about taste and the experience
of eating and therefore it's defined by taste. Okay, but it's not
either. It really depends on whether you're talking about a food הלכה
halacha or a different הלכה. halacha. Yes.
I have a little bit of a problem on how the גמרא
Gemara is trying to apply this broadly. You're saying that if המשרת
ha'mishres is its own separate איסור issur that only appears by נזיר
nazir or maybe one or two other places. Could you say this
חידוש chiddush in נזיר nazir for המשרת? ha'mishres? So how Right.
So it seems that maybe the גמרא Gemara again, maybe it's learning
it more from בכל be'chol and by the way, it's worth pointing
out a similar example would be something to think by rough analogy
is like חצי שיעור, chatzi shiur, right? You're חייב chayav if you
eat not only a כזית kezayis then you're חייב. chayav. It's a
different איסור issur but again it's a related איסור issur but not
exactly the same if you eat less than a כזית. kezayis. And
that's learned out from כל חלב. kol cheilev. So the כל kol
is coming to say not even a full amount even a less
amount, but it's not the same prohibition. You don't get מלקות malkus
and so on. Or is it a prohibition of חלב cheilev but
not enough to get מלקות malkus or is it a different prohibition?
Similar types of questions we're asking here. So you're right, if משרת
mishres was conceptually a different category it would not you couldn't apply
it. But maybe it's learning out from the כל kol that it's
actually not a category of prohibiting תערובות ta'arovos mixtures of wine, which
is what we've been saying, but maybe it's learning out no, it's
telling you a חידוש chiddush of טעם כעיקר. ta'am k'ikar. That's the
way this approach is learning it. And that's what אביי Abaye wants
to say. Why don't you know to take the טעם כעיקר ta'am
k'ikar approach here? So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אמר
ליה Amar lei so that's the question. But maybe משרת mishres is
the basis of טעם כעיקר. ta'am k'ikar. אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן לרבי
אבהו, Amar lei hahu me'rabbanan le'Rabbi Abbahu, כי קאמר לה רב עקיבא
ki ka'amar lah Rav Akiva לרבי עקיבא. le'Rabbi Akiva.
So one of the rabbis said back to אביי, Abaye, no, because
when רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu was saying that it was
היתר מצטרף לאיסור, heter mitztaref le'issur, he was only saying it according
to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva because we're going to see that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva clearly understands that the idea of משרת mishres is
היתר מצטרף לאיסור. heter mitztaref le'issur. But you know what? In general,
אביי, Abaye, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu would say that all other תנאים
tannaim say like this ברייתא braisa that you just quoted, say that
משרת mishres is the general תורה Torah principle of טעם כעיקר. ta'am
k'ikar. When he was saying משרת mishres was this more powerful but
more limited principle of היתר מצטרף לאיסור, heter mitztaref le'issur, he was
only saying it according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, now. הי
רבי עקיבא? Hei Rabbi Akiva? Which
רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Or לה lah has two or those three
things that make it more weighted. Okay, which רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva?
אילימא רבי עקיבא דהכא, Ilima Rabbi Akiva de'hacha, the רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva of our משנה. mishna. דתנן, De'tenan, רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva
omer אפילו שרה פיתו ביין ויש בה כדי לצרף כזית חייב, afilu
shar pito be'yayin ve'yesh bah k'dei letzatref kezayis chayav, even if you
dipped your bread in wine and there is enough to combine a
כזית kezayis you're חייב. chayav. וממאי? U'mimmay? How do you know that's
the principle of היתר מצטרף לאיסור? heter mitztaref le'issur? דילמא הוא דאיכא
כזית בעיני, Dilma hu de'ika kezayis be'einay, maybe it doesn't mean that
you eat a כזית kezayis of the bread and wine combined, maybe
it means you've eaten enough bread so you've ingested a full כזית
kezayis of wine? לצרף Letzatref doesn't mean to combine wine with bread.
It means to combine all the wine in the bread to a
כזית. kezayis. And that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying you have
to ingest a כזית kezayis worth of wine. וכי תימא מאי למימרא?
Ve'chi teima mai le'meimra? So what's the חידוש? chiddush? לאפוקי מתנא קמא
דאמר עד שישתה רביעית יין Le'afokei mi'tanna kamma de'amar ad she'yishteh revi'is
yayin to say the תנא קמא tanna kamma says you need to
drink a רביעית revi'is of wine, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is going
to say I'll give you an example where you could eat wine
and it wouldn't be defined by a רביעית, revi'is, it would be
defined by a כזית. kezayis. So that's a very reasonable read of
the משנה. mishna. He's not telling you you combine the bread with
the wine. He's saying if you wind up eating wine rather than
drinking wine it goes by a כזית. kezayis. So that's not רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא רבי עקיבא דברייתא,
Ela Rabbi Akiva de'braisa, fine, but in the ברייתא braisa רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is clearer and that presumably also shows you what רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in the משנה mishna says.
דתניא, De'tanya, it was taught in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי עקיבא אומר,
Rabbi Akiva omer, נזיר ששרה פיתו ביין ואכל כזית מן מיין. miyayin.
A נזיר Nazir who drenched his bread in wine and ate a
כזית kezayis of combined bread and wine, חייב. chayav. So he's very
clear, you measure the כזית kezayis by the combination. So basically the
answer is you're right. There's a ברייתא, Baraita, by the way if
you look at the מדרשי הלכה Midreshei Halacha on the פסוק pasuk
of משרת ענבים mishras anavim you see both דרשות. drashos. You see
a דרשה drasha of משרת ענבים mishras anavim to tell you the
principle of טעם כעיקר ta'am ke'ikar and you see, if I remember
correctly, the דרשה drasha of היתר מצטרף לאיסור. heter mitztaref l'issur. So
when אביי Abaye says why are we sticking with היתר מצטרף לאיסור,
heter mitztaref l'issur, משרת mishras is a basis of this big תורה
Torah principle called טעם כעיקר, ta'am ke'ikar, the answer is you're right,
but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns it in a more narrow way.
He learns it as a more powerful הלכה halacha of היתר מצטרף
לאיסור, heter mitztaref l'issur, but more narrow applying only to a נזיר.
Nazir. So then the remaining question is going to be okay, but
then where does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva know this תורה Torah principle
called טעם כעיקר? ta'am ke'ikar? Okay, which is the next question because
we're going to assume that everybody holds of it. אלא, Ela, so
the גמרא Gemara says מנא ליה? minalei? אמר ליה רב אחא בריה
דרב אביה לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Acha brei deRav Avya leRav
Ashi, so now רב אחא Rav Acha said to רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, רבי עקיבא דקמוקי ליה להאי וכל משרת להיתר מצטרף לאיסור, Rabbi
Akiva d'kamuki lei lehai v'chol mishras l'heter mitztaref l'issur, according to רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says וכל משרת v'chol mishras is for this
more narrow, more powerful but more narrow principle of
היתר מצטרף לאיסור, heter mitztaref l'issur, טעם כעיקר מנא ליה? ta'am ke'ikar
minalei? Where does he know about this principle of טעם כעיקר? ta'am
ke'ikar? Now you see why this is the סוגיא sugya that's learned
at the beginning of learning טרפות, treifos, because basically after you get
through all that כזית בכדי אכילת פרס kezayis bichdei achilas pras and
היתר מצטרף לאיסור, heter mitztaref l'issur, you get to this question of
where is the principle of טעם כעיקר, ta'am ke'ikar, which is the
principle of, oh, when איסור issur is mixed up with היתר, heter,
how do you know it's not בטל? batel? How do you know
it's still a problem if you can still taste it? Okay, so
where does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva get it from? So the גמרא
Gemara says מנא ליה? minalei? יליף מבשר בחלב. yalif mibasar bechalav. He
learns it out from cooking meat and milk. Because if you cook
meat in milk, this is why I mentioned the example before, you
only wind up with the taste of the milk in the meat.
You don't see the milk. And again, it's, you know, we experience
that more as that it's just, you know, the taste of it.
It's בשר, basar, right?
Yeah, well, בשר basar cooked in חלב, chalav, but the בשר basar
is what we're focusing on, right. Or what you could say is
the חלב. chalav. If the חלב chalav only got the taste of
the meat in it, it didn't get the meat itself. Maybe that's
even a better example, right? The
meat into the milk would be טעמו וממשו. ta'amo umamasho. The meat
into the milk, if you removed the meat and you just drank
the milk, would be טעמו ולא ממשו, ta'amo velo mamasho,
right? And nevertheless, you can't eat them, even though they only absorbed
the taste of the other. So you see the taste is like
the thing itself.
לאו טעם בעלמא, lav ta'am b'alma, it would only absorb the taste,
ואסור. v'assur. הכי נמי לא שנא. hachi nami lo shana. Here too.
So that tells you that there's a principle that the טעם ta'am
is like the thing itself. So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's,
if that's true, why did we need to learn it from משרת?
mishras? רבנן, Rabbanan, so the רבנן Rabbanan would say back, בשר בחלב
לא גמרינן דחידוש הוא. basar bechalav lo gamrinan d'chidush hu. No, no,
no, that's a whole חידוש, chidush, that's a whole special category. You
can't apply outside of that. Why? מאי חידושיה? mai chidushei? What's unique
about it, distinctive about it that you can't say it's a, we
learn principles from it? אילימא דהאי לחודיה והאי לחודיה שרי, eilyma d'hai
lechudei v'hai lechudei sharei,
maybe because meat by itself is permissible and milk by itself is
permissible, ובהדי הדדי אסיר ubehadei hadadei assir and combined they're forbidden. So
because that's very bizarre, that you combine two things that are permissible
and get something that's forbidden, right? So that, therefore, it's a, you
can't learn any principles from it.
It's a paradox of בשר בחלב. basar bechalav.
Right. So the גמרא Gemara says it's sort of like salt, right?
Sodium and chlorine, right? Isn't that what salt is? Yes. Two poisonous
things, but you combine them together it becomes the essential of life.
Even more poisonous.
No, but becomes, anyway. So it's the reverse, okay? Two מותר muttar
things, you combine them and they become forbidden. Is that so, is
that so unique says the גמרא? Gemara? כלאים איכא, kilayim ika,
so by כלאים, kilayim, האי לחודיה שרי והאי לחודיה שרי, hai lechudei
sharei v'hai lechudei sharei, grapes is permissible and wheat is permissible, ובהדי
הדדי אסיר ubehadei hadadei assir combined is forbidden. So there, that's a
normal thing that we find. That's not unique enough to say you
can't learn from it. אלא, Ela, no, here's what's unique about it.
דתרה ליה כולי יומא בחלבא. detara lei kulei yoma bechalva.
Let's say you soaked the meat in milk and that, a whole
day, and by the end of the day when you bit into
the milk meat, because it's porous, you could taste the milk. So
you tasted meat in milk, but you didn't cook it. שרי, Sharei,
it would not become forbidden biblically speaking. ומבשיל ליה בישולי, umvashil lei
bishulei, when you cook it אסור, assur, it's forbidden. So it's bizarre,
why does it need to be cooked? And the fact, you know,
you could combine them without cooking them, you could have a, you
know, salami and cheese sandwich and biblically it's not a problem, and
only when you cook them it's a problem, or you could blend
them together and it's not a problem and you taste them both.
So clearly it's a weird הלכה halacha and you can't learn from
it. Now, besides saying that it's a weird הלכה, halacha, it's a,
there's a sharper way of articulating what the גמרא Gemara might be
getting at, which is, whoever told you that the prohibition of בשר
בחלב basar bechalav was not to eat the taste of meat commingled
with the taste of milk, right, and that's your basis of saying,
or not to eat meat commingled with milk, and then you could
say, well, therefore I just got the taste, how could that be
אסור? assur? It proves that the taste is like the thing itself.
That's what we're trying to say. This meat-milk just has the taste
of meat, it shows that the taste is like the thing itself.
That's if you define the prohibition of don't eat the taste of
meat, don't eat, it said not the taste, don't eat meat and
milk mingled together, right? Co-mingled or somehow and therefore I could say,
well, I don't have meat, I guess I just have taste. Ah,
you see taste of meat is like meat. No, you know what
the prohibition of בשר בחלב Basar Be-Chalav is? Don't eat what? You
tell me, what's the prohibition, Torah's prohibition of בשר בחלב? Basar Be-Chalav?
You tell me.
לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו. Lo Tevashel Gedi Ba-Chalev Imo.
Right, but the don't eat part of it is, don't eat meat
and milk together. No, that has been cooked together. Something is defined
as בשר בחלב Basar Be-Chalav not because it's a mixture of the
tastes, but because they've been cooked together, right? In theory, if it
was maybe possible to cook meat and milk together without any transfer
of taste occurring, maybe I would also be בשר בחלב דאורייתא. Basar
Be-Chalav De-Oraita. Now the גמרא Gemara says that's not true because if
you do manage to do that, it's not דרך בישול. Derech Bishul.
Part of the whole point of בישול Bishul is to achieve a
transfer of taste. But the prohibition is not defined as the mixture
of meat and milk. The prohibition is, don't eat meat that was
cooked with milk. Don't eat milk that was cooked with meat. The
fact that in this milk I only have the taste of meat
doesn't prove that the taste of meat is like meat because it's
not forbidden because of the taste of meat, it's forbidden because it
was cooked with meat. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
I will show you, you can soak them together, you can blend
them together and it's permissible. So it is not because of the
meat and milk that are both present that you are transgressing, it
is because they have been cooked together that you are transgressing and
therefore it's not relevant to the question of whether טעם Ta'am is
like the thing itself.
I just want to also make sure I understand it clearly, so
according to that read,
the איסור Issur בשר בחלב Basar Be-Chalav for הנאה Hana'ah and for
אכילה Achilah are in a way derivative of the primary איסור Issur
of cooking it together?
That is correct and that's one of the first big questions when
you're learning בשר בחלב, Basar Be-Chalav, yes.
The Torah says לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו, Lo Tevashel Gedi Ba-Chalev
Imo,
right?
So what about cooking milk in a, I mean,
that's one direction.
Yeah, so that's an interesting question whether the Torah's fundamentally forbidding the
meat or is it fundamentally, anyway, all interesting questions next time we
learn חולין. Chullin. Moving on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay so you can't learn from בשר בחלב, Basar Be-Chalav, that
might be because they've been cooked together, not because the taste counts
like the same. So the גמרא Gemara says רבי עקיבא נמי בשר
בחלב חידוש הוא. Rabbi Akiva nami Basar Be-Chalav chidush hu. You know
what, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would have to concede that point or
he might have to concede that point.
אלא, Ela, I'm sorry, no, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say back,
one minute, wait. Yes, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would have to
concede that point. So where's he going to learn טעם כעיקר? Ta'am
Ke-Ikkar? אלא יליף מגיעולי עובדי כוכבים. Ela yalif mi-gi'ulei ovdei kochavim. He
learns from the spewing out of the vessels of the non-Jews, okay,
which is the basically when they take the vessels from מדין Midian
and the כלי מדין Klei Midian and then they have to go
through this process. Now the simplest sense of the פסוקים Pesukim might
be more a process of טהרה Tahara than a process of כשרות,
Kashrut, but halachically we read it as a process of כשרות Kashrut
that they couldn't use it because they were used for cooking טריפה
Treifa things. So why can't you use a vessel that was cooked
with טריפה, Treifa, that cooked טריפה? Treifa? Because the taste of the
טריפה Treifa will go into your food. Well, that's a principle, that
the taste is by itself is problematic, right? Because so let's take
a look. דאמר רחמנא כל דבר אשר יבא באש, De-amar Rachmana kol
davar asher yavo ba-esh, anything that was brought into a fire, meaning
cooked over a fire, you have to כשר Kasher it over a
fire, that's the way we're reading it.
וגמר דאסורי עובדי כוכבים, U-gemar de-assurei ovdei kochavim, that they're forbidden to
use without doing this. So גיעולי עובדי כוכבים לאו טעמא בעלמא הוא?
Gi'ulei ovdei kochavim lav ta'ama be-alma hu? That itself is only the
taste, ואסור, ve-assur, and it's forbidden because all it does is it
gives that taste of חזיר Chazir into the food now that you're
cooking. So הכא נמי לא שנא. Hacha nami lo shna. You see
now that's a good point. Presumably the whole problem there is that
the taste of forbidden food gets transferred into your food. So that's
why you don't have to learn it from משרת. Mishrat. And that's
why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva can use משרת Mishrat for something else.
הגמרא Ha-Gemara says ורבנן נמי תיפוק ליה מגיעולי עובדי כוכבים? ve-Rabbanan nami
tipok leh mi-gi'ulei ovdei kochavim? So the Rabbis who learn it from
משרת, Mishrat, why don't they learn it from the non-kosher כלים? Kelim?
אמר לך התם חידוש הוא. Amar lach hatam chidush hu. That's also
a חידוש. Chidush. What's the חידוש? Chidush? It's a special הלכה, Halachah,
it's not a general principle of טעם כעיקר. Ta'am Ke-Ikkar. Why is
it not a general principle? דהא בכל התורה כולה נותן טעם לפגם
מותר, De-ha be-chol ha-Torah kullah noten ta'am le-fgam mutar, because normally if
the taste starts being a bad taste, it's our assumption is that
that's permissible. Okay, and we're going to assume that any taste that's
been absorbed in the walls of the כלי Kli and then comes
back out is going to be a little bit of an off-taste,
it's not going to improve the taste, okay. וגבי גיעולי עובדי כוכבים
אסור, ve-gabei gi'ulei ovdei kochavim assur, so even though normally if you
mix a little חזיר Chazir into your stew and it makes the
stew taste worse, okay, then it's going to be permissible, that's the
principle of טעם לפגם. Ta'am Le-Fgam. But by כלים Kelim there's an
assumption that the taste that's transferred will always be worse, okay, and
nevertheless it's forbidden. So you see it is not part of a
general principle of טעם, Ta'am, it's some special הלכה Halachah that כלים
Kelim are forbidden even though it doesn't follow the general rule. So
if all we had was כלים, keilim, we might not know there's
a general principle of טעם. ta'am. There might be a special איסור
issur of don't use כלים keilim that was cooked with טרייף treif
things. If you actually had here's the irony: חזיר, chazir, a drop
of חזיר chazir that fell into your soup, and you have like
a חזיר chazir taste, a good חזיר chazir taste, maybe that's permissible,
if you didn't have משרת mishras or whatever. But nevertheless, the Torah
would still say, don't use כלים keilim that were used to cook
חזיר. chazir. Okay? So because the principle of כלים keilim doesn't follow
the normal rules of טעם, ta'am, it's a problem even when the
טעם ta'am is bad, it's not a basis for the principle of
טעם, ta'am, it might be based on its own rules. Now, one
minute, let's finish this point. So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי עקיבא
נמי הכי אית ליה, Rabbi Akiva nami hachi it lei, so wouldn't
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva have to concede that the taste that comes
off of כלים keilim is an off taste and it's a special,
it's a separate הלכה halacha and it can't be a basis for
this principle? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב הונא בר חייא
לא אסרה תורה אלא קדירה בת יומא דלאו נותן טעם לפגם הוא.
Amar Rav Huna bar Chiyya lo asra Torah ela kdeira bat yoma
delav noten ta'am lifgam hu. No, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say
that the תורה Torah is only forbidding to use the vessel on
the same day, right? This is the reason why if בדיעבד bedi'avad
you cooked with your thing and it was more than 24 hours
it's okay, it's because we say אינו בן יומו, eino ben yomo,
because we say it gives off a טעם לפגם. ta'am lifgam. So
the גמרא Gemara is saying that therefore when they took the vessels
from מדין, Midian, it was only forbidden to use them on that
day itself. If they would have waited 24 hours, it would have
been טעם לפגם, ta'am lifgam, it would have been okay. Of course,
the ראשונים Rishonim all say, why would they go to such a
process of having to כשר kasher everything if you just wait 24
hours? Because they wanted to eat that day with those vessels! I
mean, the whole reason that we לכתחילה lechatchila don't do it is
because as מדרבנן miderabbanan you're not allowed to, but דאורייתא de'oraita you
would be. Anyway, whatever the answer to that is, the גמרא Gemara
says that no, it fits the normal rules of taste, and the
טעם ta'am was good on the same day, and that's why you
can't use the vessels and it is a basis for the normal
rules of taste. Because so let's see what the רבנן Rabbanan would
say back. If that's true that it was only אסור assur on
the same day and it fits the normal rules of taste, why
isn't that the basis for those rules? So the גמרא Gemara says,
לרבנן קדירה בת יומא נמי אי אפשר דלא פגמה פורתא. LeRabbanan kdeira
bat yoma nami ee efshar d'la pagma purta.
No,
I disagree, even on the same day it's a taste that's a
little bit off, and since the taste is a little bit off
even on the same day, it even on the day itself it
does not fit the normal rules of taste, and therefore cannot be
the basis for the principle of טעם כעיקר. ta'am ke'ikar. Now, I
want to tell you, well yes, that's a question about which way
these we פסקן, pasken, and would even they they concede there's a
difference between the first day and later days and the חידוש chiddush
is only on the first day? So
they might agree to the idea that it's only אסור assur on
the first day because then it's only a little off as opposed
to a lot off. But now, like I just said to you
by בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, rather than saying 'oh it's a special
rule' and make it not inter- you know, okay, it's like a
black hole, a special rule you can't learn from it. But okay,
what is the special rule? And here, let me by the way
sharpen it because while we're saying that there's this principle of טעם
כעיקר, ta'am ke'ikar, it's worth pointing out that according to a lot
of ראשונים, Rishonim, okay, there's a big question to what degree we
פסקן pasken טעם כעיקר ta'am ke'ikar is דאורייתא. de'oraita. Some ראשונים Rishonim
say we actually might, we don't actually פסקן pasken it's דאורייתא de'oraita
at all, which is like radical. Okay, but even assuming it is
דאורייתא, de'oraita, many ראשונים Rishonim say that we only פסקן pasken it's
דאורייתא de'oraita if it is, they combine the two discussions yesterday's and
today's, and say only if there's so much mixed in that it's
כזית בכדי אכילת פרס. kezayit bichdei achilat pras. So if you actually
have so much חזיר chazir mixed in, like a one to nine
or one to eight ratio, that you could eat a כזית kezayit
of חזיר chazir בכדי אכילת פרס, bichdei achilat pras, that would be
טעם כעיקר דאורייתא. ta'am ke'ikar de'oraita. But if you only have a
few drops of חזיר chazir mixed in, that's only מדרבנן. miderabbanan. That's
what some ראשונים Rishonim say. Some say any amount that gives taste
is דאורייתא, de'oraita, but others say only כזית בכדי אכילת פרס. kezayit
bichdei achilat pras. So here's the question which is asked by the
רא"ה, Ra'ah, if you only transgress דאורייתא de'oraita by כזית בכדי אכילת
פרס, kezayit bichdei achilat pras, how do you explain the איסור issur
of כלי מדין? klei Midian? Right? It's a variation of the גמרא's
Gemara question. There's not enough taste that's transferring, okay, so it's a
variation of the גמרא's Gemara question which points to the idea that
the כלי מדין klei Midian might be a different category. And the
difference would be the following. The difference is the reason it's אסור
assur to use a טרייף treif vessel is not because the טרייפות
treifus goes into the walls and into the food and it makes
the food אסור. assur. The reason is because the תורה Torah tells
you, only use כשר kasher vessels, don't use טרייף treif vessels. Something
that was cooked with טרייף treif labels the vessel as off limits,
right? It's a חזיר chazir vessel. Don't use חזיר chazir vessels, only
use כשר kasher vessels, right? And that's the הלכה. halacha. The הלכה
halacha is less about the taste that will transfer and more about
the identity of the vessel. Okay, and that's also an important principle
when you're learning laws of כשרות. kashrus. How much do we think
that the whole ideas of כשר'ינג kashering כלים keilim and all of
that is because of the embedded taste that then will transfer and
it's ultimately about טרייף'ינג treifing up the food, and how much is
it the fact that it was cooked with טרייף treif labels it?
Because you know, for anybody learning כשרות, kashrus, the big question is,
really? You expect me to believe in our stainless steel, non-porous vessels,
a taste really goes in and we have to worry about all
this type of stuff, etc., etc.? And the answer might be, and
why don't we just go ahead and like taste it or do
other... anyway, the answer to that is... Some of that might be,
"You're right. Maybe it has a lot less to do with actual
absorbed and transferred taste and more has to do with the identity
of the vessel," which also might explain why it's only forbidden דאורייתא
doraisa on the day itself. Because on the day that it was
used, like it keeps that clear identity. Once it becomes like past
history, maybe that identity is less central.
Is the category of בן יומו ben yomo also exactly paradigm of
identity and not of chemistry?
Exactly. Exactly. Right. So both בשר בחלב basar bechalav might not be
about the tastes being mixed together, it might be about the fact
of being cooked together, and it's not a basis for taste. And
כלים kelim might not be a basis of the taste that goes
into the vessel's transferred, it might be a question about the identity
of the כלי kli as a טרייף treif כלי. kli. Don't use
טרייף כלים. treif kelim. Okay, and it focuses on the כלי kli
and not on the food. Yeah.
But theoretically, it's all a little bit funny because, you know, what
was the איסור? issur? The איסור issur was that
they אכלם מזבחי אלוהים... achlam mizevachei elohim...
Okay, I don't want to go there.
Fine. So the פת pas is not אסור assur because of טרייף
treif but עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But that's one thing. The other
thing is what do we get from there, you know, if I
want to address the point, but that you know somehow we also
kashered a new vessel, right? Which was not cooked.
Okay, that's a different thing, but that actually reinforces it. The very
fact that חז"ל chazal also learn out the idea of kashering but
being טובל tovel a new vessel reinforces the idea that this is
about the vessel's identity. The fact that from the same פרשה parsha
in the תורה Torah we learn kashering and being טובל tovel points
more to the איסור issur about the identity.
Then you'd kasher a vessel not just like a new vessel, right?
Meaning, is that what you're saying? Because we have to טובל tovel
even a new vessel.
Yeah. Right. So all of them is about giving it a type
of an identity. Yes.
This identity thing, but also, if I remember correctly, when you kasher
a vessel, it's according to its usual...
Excellent. So that's one of the נפקא מינות, nafkaminas, right? Why is
it that when you kasher it, it's based on its majority use?
Who cares about the majority use? If once it was used in
a particular way, like if once you use it directly over fire
but most of the time you cook something, like, its things transfer
with water, it's enough to kasher it by immersing it in water.
But why is that true? If once it was used directly over
the fire and it absorbed taste in a more serious way, that
taste is still lingering, you still need to get that taste out.
Why is it enough to kasher it in based on its normal
use? That's one of the נפקא מינות nafkaminas I give when I'm
giving that שיעור. shiur. It exactly shows that it's much more about
its identity. Yes.
There's a term here that I—we haven't really used. It's now used
all over the place. Called כל התורה כולה. kol hatorah kula. Yeah.
So is that in other words, you have anything to say about
that like
it—no, I mean it just means it's a—no, no, it doesn't mean
דאורייתא, doraisa, it means don't limit it to the case in which
we find it. Don't limit it to נזיר nazir or to בשר
בחלב basar bechalav or to כלים. kelim. It becomes a principle that
applies across categories. Right. All right, so let's keep on going. So
now we have two—as you can see, why there's such a rich
סוגיא sugya is we have A, the question of the principle of
טעם כעיקר, taam ke'ikkar, but B, how do you think about בשר
בחלב? basar bechalav? How do you think about כלים? kelim? Do you
think about them as a type of a טעם taam issue or
do you think about them distinct? So now the גמרא gemara says
like this. Oh, so we still don't have a source now or
clear source according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Maybe it's כלים, kelim,
if you say בת יומא, bas yomo, but that's sort of what
we're left with, that maybe כלים kelim is the source. אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרב אבירא לרב אשי. Amar lei Rav Acha berei
deRav Avira leRav Ashi. מדרבנן, Miderabbanan, so that we seem to be
okay with that, that maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in the end
gets it from the idea of כלי מדין klei midyan and that
that does fit the normal parameters of טעם. taam. But now he
says look, from the Rabbis, why don't we say the same thing
for Rabbi—what the Rabbis' approach to משרת mistrah should be רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva's approach to משרת. mistrah.
לאו אמרי רבנן האי משרת ויתן טעם כעיקר. Lav amri rabbanan hai
mistrah veyitein taam ke'ikkar. The Rabbis say משרת mistrah is the טעם
כעיקר taam ke'ikkar principle, that בשר בחלב basar bechalav and כלי מדין
klei midyan are special חידושים, chidushim, טעם כעיקר taam ke'ikkar is based
on משרת. mistrah. But then they say מכאן אתה דן לכל איסורים
שבתורה, mikan atah dan lekhol issurin shebatorah, that we apply this principle
of טעם כעיקר taam ke'ikkar to all cases of forbidden foods in
the תורה. Torah. They make this a principle. So רבי עקיבא נמי,
Rabbi Akiva nami, so why don't we say the same for רבי
עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? He learned טעם כעיקר taam ke'ikkar from somewhere else,
I don't know, from כלי מדין. klei midyan. Fine. What does he
do with משרת? mistrah? דקא מוקי ליה להאי משרת להיתר מצטרף לאיסור.
Dekamoiki lei lehai mistrah leheter mitztaref le'issur. This more intense principle of
היתר מצטרף לאיסור. heter mitztaref le'issur. So why does he keep that
narrow? לימא מכאן אתה דן לכל איסורים שבתורה. Leima mikan atah dan
lekhol issurin shebatorah. Why doesn't he broaden it? The Rabbis broadened it
because they said the איסור issur of נזיר nazir is a light
איסור, issur, יש היתר לאיסורו, yesh heter le'issuro, אין איסורו איסור הנאה,
ein issuro issur hanaah, we can use the principle by נזיר nazir
to apply to all forbidden foods in the תורה. Torah. So why
doesn't רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say the same about היתר מצטרף לאיסור?
heter mitztaref le'issur? Okay, that's a good question. What lets him limit
היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref le'issur just to נזיר? nazir? So the
גמרא gemara says like this. אמר ליה משום דהוי נזיר וחטאת שני
כתובים הבאים כאחד. Amar lei mishum dehavei nazir vechatas shnei kesuvim habaim
ke'echad.
Because by a קרבן חטאת korban chatas we also find the principle
of היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref le'issur and there's an idea that
if you find something mentioned in two places, we assume that the
reason the תורה Torah had to say it twice is because the
cases are exceptions. If it was a rule, it would have said
it once and you could have applied the rule. But if it's
saying it twice, it's telling you that these are the exceptions. It's
שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. shnei kesuvim habaim ke'echad. So where do we
see היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref le'issur by חטאת? chatas? Okay, right.
אימא למדי. Eima lamdi. נזיר... Nazir... נזיר הדאמר, Nazir hada amar, we
said נזיר. Nazir. חטאת, Chatas, שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין למדין, Shenei
kesuvim habaim ke-echad ein lemadin, and you cannot apply as a general
principle something that occurs, an identical rule that occurs in two different
cases. Okay, now another הדאמר, hada amar, נזיר Nazir we said משרת.
meshuras. חטאת מהי? Chatas mahi? דתניא. de-tanya. תניא בריתא: tanya baraita: כל
אשר יגע בבשרה יקדש, Kol asher yiga bivsara yikdash,
anything that touches the flesh of the חטאת Chatas will become sanctified.
What does that mean? יכול אפילו שלא בלע? Yachol afilu shelo bala?
Maybe first of all just the act of touching without absorbing? תלמוד
לומר בבשרה, Talmud lomar bivsara, in its flesh. עד שיבלע
בבשרתו, Ad she-yivla bivsarato, something actually gets absorbed, actually that sounds like
the thing is going into the flesh of the חטאת, Chatas, but
anyway, it means something is going in. So it's absorbing from the
very juices of the חטאת. Chatas. יקדש להיות כמוה, Yikdash lihyot kamocha,
it becomes sanctified to take on the status of the חטאת. Chatas.
Like let's say a שלמים Shlamim touched a חטאת Chatas or a
piece of bread touched a חטאת. Chatas. שאם פסולה היא תפסל, She-im
pesula hi yipassel,
if the חטאת Chatas had been invalid for some reason, shechted for
the wrong reason or something, then the other thing also becomes invalid
with the בליעה. bli-ah. ואי כשרה, Ve-im keshera, and if the חטאת
Chatas was a כשרה keshera חטאת, Chatas, תאכל כחמור שבה. tochal ke-chomer
she-ba. It has to be eaten in the more stringent way. So
the classic example if a שלמים Shlamim touched a חטאת, Chatas, a
חטאת Chatas can only be eaten by כהנים Kohanim and only eaten
for one day. So therefore the שלמים Shlamim that absorbed from the
חטאת Chatas also has the same rules. Now that's not yet היתר
מצטרף לאיסור. hetter mitztaref le-issur. That just tells you that's more like
טעם כעיקר. ta-am k-ikar. You have some of the חטאת Chatas in
the שלמים. Shlamim. Okay, or maybe it's a special הלכה halacha by
חטאת Chatas that the whole שלמים Shlamim is defined by it, not
just the area that has that taste. But anyway, that's still not
היתר מצטרף לאיסור. hetter mitztaref le-issur. That idea we haven't seen yet.
For the שלמים Shlamim it's just the part that touches it, right?
They don't have to cut off...
it's not the whole שלמים? Shlamim? Well, presumably, presumably. Okay, so let's
take a look, but still not היתר מצטרף לאיסור. hetter mitztaref le-issur.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, now one minute. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't exactly spell out
how you know that even though it has this הלכה halacha that
it's really a principle of היתר מצטרף לאיסור. hetter mitztaref le-issur. So
I think תוספות Tosafot say one minute.
Yeah, so in the middle of תוספות תאכל, Tosafot Tochal, תוספות Tosafot
says the following. If you take a look like almost exactly in
the middle the line starts with the word השלמים. Ha-Shlamim. So תוספות
Tosafot says: השלמים הרי גלי רחמנא בחטאת דהיתר מצטרף לאיסור. Ha-Shlamim: harei
gali Rachmana be-Chatas de-hetter mitztaref le-issur. דמי לא עסקינן? Di-mi lo askinan?
Wouldn't we even be talking about a case דנבלע חצי זית שומן
בתוך חצי זית דחולין או חצי זית דשלמים, de-nivla chatzi zayit shuman
betoch chatzi zayit de-chullin o chatzi zayit de-shlamim, that a half of
a זית zayit of the fat of a חטאת Chatas got absorbed
into a half a זית zayit שלמים? Shlamim? להכי איצטריך, Le-hachi itztarich,
so that's
what you need it for. You already have a principle of טעם
כעיקר. ta-am k-ikar. Meaning what תוספות Tosafot is saying is it's not
so satisfying, but he's saying look, according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
we know טעם כעיקר ta-am k-ikar from somewhere else. We know טעם
כעיקר ta-am k-ikar from let's say the כלי מדין. klei Midian. Let's
say we assume that. So if there's already a general principle of
טעם כעיקר, ta-am k-ikar, why would the תורה Torah then also be
telling me the הלכה halacha that if a שלמים Shlamim absorbed the
taste of a חטאת, Chatas, you have to treat it like a
חטאת? Chatas? Of course, we have a principle of טעם כעיקר, ta-am
k-ikar, so if it has the taste of a חטאת, Chatas, you
gotta treat it like a חטאת. Chatas. So if the תורה Torah
is telling me this idea again by a חטאת, Chatas, it must
be telling me that it goes even further by a חטאת Chatas
and that it's a principle of היתר מצטרף לאיסור. hetter mitztaref le-issur.
That if you eat a כזית k-zayit of this שלמים Shlamim that
has absorbed חטאת Chatas in it
and it's פסול, passul, you'd actually get lashes like eating a full
כזית k-zayit of a חטאת. Chatas. It's not so clear how you
get that from the פסוק, pasuk, but anyway, that's what we're reading.
It's not just telling you טעם כעיקר, ta-am k-ikar, we know טעם
כעיקר, ta-am k-ikar, it's telling you the whole thing becomes like a
חטאת, Chatas, even the היתר hetter becomes like a חטאת, Chatas, היתר
מצטרף לאיסור. hetter mitztaref le-issur. So you have two פסוקים pesukim and
you cannot apply it elsewhere. Let's just finish this. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: ורבנן? Ve-rabbanan?
So the Rabbis would say back: צריכי. tzerichi. No, it had to
be written in both places. The only time you say you can't
apply from two cases is if it's redundant. But if it's needed
to be said in both cases, then it's not redundant, it still
remains a principle. Why is it not redundant? דאי כתב רחמנא גבי
חטאת, Di-i ketav Rachmana gabei Chatas, if it had said it by
חטאת, Chatas, הוה אמינא נזיר לא אתי מיניה. hava amina Nazir lo
ati minei. דנזיר מקדשים לא ילפינן. De-Nazir mi-kodashim lo yafinan. Stringency said
by קדשים kodashim can't won't apply to normal איסורין. issurin. So obviously
it was not sufficient to write it by חטאת. Chatas. So we
just write it by נזיר. Nazir. ואי כתב רחמנא גבי נזיר, Ve-i
ketav Rachmana gabei Nazir, had it just been written by נזיר, Nazir,
הוה אמינא מנזיר לא ילפינן. hava amina mi-Nazir lo yafinan. No, you
can't learn out קדשים kodashim from נזיר. Nazir. Why not? If it's
אסור assur by נזיר, Nazir, it should be אסור assur by other
things. No, משום דחומרא דאיסוריה, mishum de-chomer issurei,
because נזיר Nazir is a weighty category. Why is נזיר Nazir a
weighty category? דאפילו חרצן אסור, De-afilu chartzan assur, even things like the
skin or the pits are אסור. assur. So maybe I would have
said that that's particularly weighty by נזיר Nazir and these are special
stringencies. Yeah, I know, that's what's bizarre. And let's also not forget
that the Rabbis say משרת meshuras of טעם כעיקר ta-am k-ikar by
נזיר Nazir applies everywhere. So they don't think נזיר Nazir is such
an exception. הלכך לא אתי מיניה. Hilkach lo ati minei.
Therefore you can't learn it. So somehow the Rabbis said no, if
it had just been written in those two places, I would not
have made it a... I would not have said that you can't
learn it as a general rule. רבי עקיבא אמר לך... Rabbi Akiva
amar lach... Rabbi Akiva would say back to you, למה צריכי, Lema
tzarichi, what do you mean? You don't need them both places. בשלמא
דכתב רחמנא חטאת לא גמירי נזיר מיניה, Bishlama de-ktav rachmana chatas lo
gamir Nazir minei, yeah, if it had written by חטאת, chatas, then
you couldn't learn other things, דחומרא מקדשים לא גמרינן, De-chumra mikodshim lo
gamrinan, you can't learn stringencies from קדשים Kodshim to other places. אלא
לכתוב רחמנא בנזיר, Ela lichtov rachmana be-Nazir,
but still, just say this idea of היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref
le-issur by נזיר, Nazir, ותיתי חטאת מיניה, Ve-tisi chatas minei, and then
you should be able to apply it. And how do I know?
דהא כולי איסורים שבתורה קא גמרי מיניה דנזיר, De-ha kulei issurim she-ba-Torah
ka-gamri minei de-Nazir, you yourself say, that yeah, here it means like
you yourself say, טעם כעיקר, ta'am ke-ikar, you learn from נזיר Nazir
everywhere else. So if I'm going to say so here too, I
could have learned from נזיר Nazir everywhere else היתר מצטרף לאיסור, heter
mitztaref le-issur, and if the Torah went and repeated it, it was
to tell me not to learn, that it's an exception. One last
line, ורבנן אמרי לך, Ve-rabbanan amri lach, the rabbis will say to
you, חטאת להיתר מצטרף לאיסור וחומרא מקדשים לא גמרינן, Chatas le-heter mitztaref
le-issur ve-chumra mikodshim lo gamrinan,
you know, you're right. נזיר Nazir is a what's written by נזיר,
Nazir, like what's written by חטאת chatas stays by חטאת, chatas, but
what's written by נזיר Nazir applies everywhere. So here's what the rabbis
say. So Rabbi Akiva chooses to read נזיר Nazir and חטאת chatas
as היתר מצטרף לאיסור, heter mitztaref le-issur, and therefore he says since
חטאת chatas is redundant because if it was נזיר Nazir it would
have already applied everywhere, it tells you it's an exception. And that's
how he gets the idea of היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref le-issur
but only by נזיר Nazir and חטאת. chatas. And what the rabbis
say is, חטאת להיתר מצטרף לאיסור, Chatas le-heter mitztaref le-issur, חטאת chatas
you're right, it is היתר מצטרף לאיסור, heter mitztaref le-issur, but that's
only by קדשים. Kodshim. Okay? וחומרא מקדשים לא גמרינן, Ve-chumra mikodshim lo
gamrinan,
that's a unique law by קדשים, Kodshim, ומשרת ליתן טעם כעיקר מכאן
אתה דן לכל איסורים שבתורה. U-mishras litten ta'am ke-ikar mikan attah dan
le-chol issurim she-ba-Torah.
And משרת mishras is by נזיר, Nazir, and that applies to all
איסורים שבתורה. issurim she-ba-Torah. So it all works out very nicely. Again,
what's written by נזיר Nazir applies everywhere. The rabbis say what's written
by נזיר Nazir is טעם כעיקר, ta'am ke-ikar, that applies everywhere. You
have a special פסוק pasuk by חטאת, chatas, that's היתר מצטרף לאיסור,
heter mitztaref le-issur, which is a unique הלכה halacha by חטאת. chatas.
Rabbi Akiva says I already know טעם כעיקר ta'am ke-ikar from כלי
מדין. Klei Midyan. So, and then it says again by נזיר, Nazir,
that's telling you היתר מצטרף לאיסור. heter mitztaref le-issur. Why not say
that that applies everywhere? I would have, if that would have been
the only case, because then it would have applied everywhere. But the
fact that the Torah repeated it by קדשים, Kodshim, which it didn't
have to repeat it, teaches me that היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref
le-issur is an exception, only to be applied by נזיר Nazir and
by קדשים. Kodshim. But one way or another, we know a principle
of טעם כעיקר ta'am ke-ikar either from כלי מדין Klei Midyan according
to Rabbi Akiva, or from משרת mishras according to everyone
else.